<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay concerning adepts, or, A resolution of this inquiry how it cometh to pass that adepts, if there are any in the world, are no more beneficial to mankind than they have been known hitherto to be, and whether there could be no way to encourage them to communicate themselves : with some resolutions concerning the principles of the adeptists and a model, practicable, and easy, of living in community : in two parts / by a Philadept ...</title>
            <author>Philadept.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11286</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12277235</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12277235</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58497</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38622)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58497)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 625:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay concerning adepts, or, A resolution of this inquiry how it cometh to pass that adepts, if there are any in the world, are no more beneficial to mankind than they have been known hitherto to be, and whether there could be no way to encourage them to communicate themselves : with some resolutions concerning the principles of the adeptists and a model, practicable, and easy, of living in community : in two parts / by a Philadept ...</title>
                  <author>Philadept.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Mayos ..., and are to be sold by J. Nutt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alchemy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58497:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY Concerning ADEPTS: OR, A Reſolution of this Inquiry, How it cometh to paſs that <hi>ADEPTS,</hi> if there are any in the World, are no more Beneficial to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind than they have been known hitherto to be, and whether there could be no way to Encourage them to Communicate themſelves.</p>
            <p>With ſome Reſolutions concerning the Principles of the <hi>ADEPTISTS;</hi> And a Model, Practicable, and Eaſy, of living in Community.</p>
            <p>In Two PARTS.</p>
            <p>By a <hi>Philadept.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>God has choſen the Fooliſh things of this World, to confound the Wiſe. Prepare the way of the Lord, and make his Paths ſtraight. Quench not the Light of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Touch not mine Anointed.</q>
            <p>London: Printed by J. Mayos at the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Golden Croſs in Thames-ſtreet near Queen-Hithe, and are to be Sold by J. Nutt near Stationers-Hall. 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:58497:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58497:2"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY Concerning ADEPTS. In Two PARTS.</head>
            <argument>
               <list>
                  <head>The firſt Part.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>I. Section.</hi> THat it cannot reaſonably be denied, that there is ſuch a thing as the <hi>Philoſophers Stone..</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. That it would be a mighty Advantage, to enjoy the Benefits of it.</item>
                  <item>III. That <hi>Adepts</hi> ſay, It is no very difficult matter to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that Ineſtimable Advantage.</item>
                  <item>IV. That they are Diſcouraged from communicating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or their Medicine, as they otherwiſe would.</item>
                  <item>V. What would Encourage them to do it, and put them in a capacity to be beneficial to Men.</item>
                  <item>VI. The Inexcuſableneſs and Folly of rejecting ſuch a Bleſſing.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58497:3"/>
                  <head>The Second Part.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1. Sect.</hi> THE occaſion of the Second Part.</item>
                  <item>II. An Explication of theſe words, <hi>It is thought,</hi> Adepts <hi>wiſh that Chriſtians would live ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, after the manner of the</hi> Lacedemonians.</item>
                  <item>III. How it would be poſſible for Chriſtians to live much after that manner.</item>
                  <item>IV. That undoubtedly it would be moſt reaſonable and moſt <hi>Chriſtian-like,</hi> to follow that ſort of Life.</item>
                  <item>V. That yet <hi>Adepts</hi> cannot be thought to require expreſly ſo much, for if they pleaſed, they might eaſily reduce Men to an abſolute neceſſity to do ſo.</item>
                  <item>VI. That in general, they would undoubtedly require of men nothing but Secrecy and Fidelity, Reaſon and Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Juſtice and Mercifulneſs; and that 'tis not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, could they be aſſured of theſe, they would be ready to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat themſelves, under ſome juſt limitations.</item>
                  <item>VII. What this Condition, more particularly, may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, for inſtance, to Imply.</item>
                  <item>VIII. The Aſſurance which has been intimated that Princes might give.</item>
                  <item>IX. What Great men might reaſonably do, in order to obtain the <hi>Elixir.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58497:3"/>
               <head>The firſt Part.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>1. Section.</hi> That it cannot reaſonably be denied, that there is ſuch a thing as the <hi>Philoſophers Stone.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is, evidently, unreaſonable to aſſert or deny any thing without Reaſon, and it is conſtant no man can give any good reaſon importing that there is no ſuch thing as the <hi>Philoſophers Stone.</hi> On the contrary, there are many reaſons to believe there is ſuch a thing. There is a Tradition of it in the World. There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Books on that Subject, written by men that ſhew an extraordinary gravity, Sincerity and Fear of God, and who Solemnly and Sacredly proteſt they have wrought it with their own hands. And beſides, they have, at ſeveral times, ſhewn the effects of it before divers witneſſes; whereof there are too many inſtances, to reject this proof. Then they lay down Principles, which appear rational, to any one that conſiders them. Any man may know ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally that the <hi>Sulphur of Silver fixes Mercury.</hi> why then ſhould it be thought incredible that there is a way to get, ſomwhere, a ſufficient quantity of that <hi>Sulphur,</hi> and to exalt it, and with it to tinge the <hi>Mercury</hi> that is in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect <hi>Metals?</hi> There have been alſo too many great Cures performed by <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> to be reaſonably queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd by them who are acquainted with thoſe matters: Thoſe that are not, ought not in reaſon to determine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it: And thoſe that are acquainted with ſome of thoſe Teſtimonies, that have been given to the World, are guilty of a Diſpoſition of unbelief, if they are not mov'd at all with all thoſe proofs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58497:4"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>II. Sect.</hi> That it would be a mighty Advantage, to enjoy the benefits of the <hi>Philoſophers Stone.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MY intention is not to diſpute about the Principles of the <hi>Hermetick Philoſophy;</hi> they have been eſtabliſhed by many Authors beyond diſpute; but moſt clearly and moſt invincibly by the Learned <hi>Gaſto Claveus,</hi> of any I know: But I write for thoſe who allow there is ſuch a thing as the <hi>Sophick Stone.</hi> Now, I would only briefly mind them of the mighty advantage there is, to enjoy the Benefits it doth procure: It procures, 1. <hi>Riches, 2. Contentment and Virtue, 3. Health and Strength.</hi> As to the firſt and laſt, ſcarce any that believes that there is ſuch a thing, is unſatisfied about them. And as to Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Virtue, I would have it to be conſidered whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Man that Enjoys Health and Strength, and what he deſires and is moſt neceſſary to his well-being, has not a mighty and extraordinary inducement to be thankful to to God, to think of providing for Everlaſting Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and to Deſpiſe, in compariſon of that, all the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and the Superfluities of this World?</p>
                  <p>And if things be ſo, pray conſider the Felicity of that Man's State who poſſeſſes all things, and who actually feels no want, nor Pain or Infirmity, but lives here happy and contented, as long as the Nature of Man is fit to laſt, and after that departs Tranquillely and without Anguiſh, and with eaſe and comfort paſſeth into the Regions of the Bleſſed Children of God above.</p>
                  <p>What advantages the <hi>Sophick Stone</hi> would procure to a Nation, 'tis not neceſſary to ſpecifie, it being eaſie for every one to imagine it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>III. Sect.</hi> That <hi>Adepts</hi> ſay, It is no very difficult matter to obtain their Ineſtimable Treaſure.</head>
                  <p>A <hi>Depts</hi> affirm, that a Man that is reaſonable and a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man, and that has attentively read their writings
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58497:4"/>
and conſiders them, and obſerves the works of Nature, may, with a careful practice, thro' God's Bleſſing, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Admirable <hi>Elixir,</hi> without very much difficulty. Their matter ſome of them ſay may be taken out of many things: They ſay plainly it is a Mineral Vitriol, that is not to be had ready made, nor to be bought with mony, but the Artiſt muſt make it, ſo that 'tis not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to be common Vitriol; and they ſay 'tis not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely difficult to make it, nor doth it require much coſt, nor muſt we take any Mettal for its compoſition: Some ſay it may be found in Antimony, and ſome ſay in other things.</p>
                  <p>For my part, if all that <hi>Adepts</hi> (or reputed <hi>Adepts</hi>) ſay be true, when they ſpeak without diſguiſe, I do not believe that a man would find it an eaſy thing to run thro all the Operations to make the Elixir, even tho' he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a Receipt <hi>verbatim</hi> for it: But it may be reckoned not very difficult, in compariſon of other works incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably more Laborious, and with reſpect of the ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable profit it will bring, which ought to make all the Labours of it ſeem not grieveous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>IV. Sect.</hi> That <hi>Adepts</hi> are diſcouraged from communicating themſelves, or their Medecine, as they otherwiſe would.</head>
                  <p>I Have hitherto made way to anſwer the chief Object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the Stone. Now I ſhall more directly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, in this Section, the inquiry, how it comes to paſs, if there are <hi>Adepts</hi> in the World, that they are no more beneficial to Mankind? And for a reſolution of this, we need but obſerve the perverſe diſpoſition of the generality of men: For it is certain 'tis men's fault, and not the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>depts,</hi> that the World enjoys not the benefits of the <hi>Elixir.</hi> But what muſt <hi>Adepts</hi> do? Muſt they go communicate their Medicine to ſome Prince, who then being furniſhed with all the Treaſure of the World, will perhaps give way to his ambition, and frame the project to ſubdue to him all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58497:5"/>
the World, and ſo will fill the Earth with Confuſion and Violence? Or muſt an <hi>Adept</hi> betray himſelf to a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of wicked men, as certainly the greateſt part of men are, who, conſulting nothing but their own greedy deſires will be ready thro'their Luſt and Coveteouſneſs, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the greateſt enormities to get the poſſeſſion of that whereof they are unworthy, and which they would not know how to uſe, but to their own deſtruction and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal damnation? Certainly it muſt be confeſt, thoſe who have the <hi>Elixir</hi> can ſcarcely find ſafe oppertunities to make uſe of it to the Benefit of men, in that diſpoſition the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of men now are. And this, undoubtedly, does ſufficiently ſolve the difficulty of the inquiry: For indeed, it cannot reaſonably be look't upon as any thing elſe but a difficulty, For it can never be thought an Argument that there are no <hi>Adepts;</hi> for tho' we could give no account at all, why, ſuppoſing there be <hi>Adepts,</hi> they are no more benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to mankind, yet it would not neceſſarily follow that that ſuppoſition that there are <hi>Adepts</hi> is falſe; for it might be ſome reaſon we did not know, did hinder them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate themſelves or their Medecine to the World; for certainly we know not all things: wherefore, not taking at firſt this difficulty as a ſufficient ground to move reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable perſons to disbelieve that there are any <hi>Adepts,</hi> I ſaid, in the beginning, my deſign was only to write for them who allow the reality of the <hi>Sophick Stone,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently think there may be <hi>Hermetick Piloſophers</hi> now living, tho' at the ſame time, it may alſo ſeem ſtrange, before due conſideration, why they do no more good than we generally ſee they do, which is the occaſion of that part of the inquiry, of which I think a ſufficient account has been given:</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58497:5"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>V. Sect.</hi> What would encourage <hi>Adepts</hi> to communicate themſelves more, or what would put them in a capacity to be beneficial to Men.</head>
                  <p>I Extremely blame thoſe who inceſſantly compare the matters that relate to the <hi>Hermetick Philoſophy</hi> with the matters of Religion. But particularly, as to the Evidence of the reality of the <hi>Stone;</hi> what compariſon is there of that, with the Evidence of Religion? Doth natural Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience witneſs any thing concerning the <hi>Stone?</hi> Have any <hi>Adepts</hi> offered their lives, and magnanimouſly ſuffered Martyrdom to confirm the Truth of it?</p>
                  <p>But, on the other hand, I think thoſe cannot be excuſed, who, becauſe they have no ocular demonſtration of the Elixir, eſteem it not worth while to do the moſt reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things, to qualify them for a participation thereof.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe man ought to beware of extreams, and to weigh calmly every thing, and to proceed in his actions accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Laws of reaſon. And that, I'm ſure, will ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify whatſoever <hi>Adepts</hi> can be ſuppoſed to require of the World: That makes me the more willing to endeavour now, in ſome meaſure, to reſolve the latter part of the Inquiry. Importing, <hi>Whether there could be no way, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage</hi> Adepts <hi>to communicate themſelves more freely, then hither to they have done?</hi> I anſwer, There is without doubt; ſeeing, as has been obſerved, it is Men's fault, and not the <hi>Adepts,</hi> that the World enjoys not the benefit of the <hi>Elixir.</hi> Then the queſtion muſt be, what would encourage <hi>Adepts</hi> to communicate themſelves and their Medicine; and what would put them in a capacity to be Beneficial to Men? The Reſolution, in general, and in ſhort is, that <hi>Adepts,</hi> unqueſtionably, would freely communicate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if they ſaw Reaſon, Juſtice and Moderation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail among Men. Then they would have ground to hope, that Men would make no ill uſe of the <hi>Elixir,</hi> but would be content to make that uſe of it which reaſon and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58497:6"/>
                     <hi>Adepts</hi> ſhould direct. And that, we may ſuppoſe, would be chiefly to prevent Pains and Diſeaſes, and to free men from want, and enable them to do good to them that need; but not to move them to diſturbe and trouble o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, and pretend to domineer over and command all the World, 'Tis certain, <hi>Adepts</hi> think there are few juſt cauſes of War, except that which is made for a Peoples own defence. They abhor all violence and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ambition and oppreſſion: For certainly God abhors theſe things, and they are, evidently, directly contrary to Reaſon. But what aſſurance could <hi>Adepts</hi> have, that a People would be Juſt and Moderate, and which way could it be aſcertained, that men for the future would entertain Moderation and Juſtice? Why, Magiſtrates being exemplary in thoſe Virtues, and taking ſolemnly a particular Oath that they would conſtantly perſevere in them, and keep Faith with <hi>Adepts;</hi> that would be a great encouragement to <hi>Adepts</hi> to communicate themſelves to ſome of them for the Univerſal good of their People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is undoubted, <hi>Adepts</hi> look upon all men to be Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Equals, and therefore would have all men to be alike happy, if they would be ſwayed by Juſtice and Reaſon. Their chief learning conſiſting in that of Piety and the Fear of God, they cannot but obſerve that the Chriſtian Religion forbids an immoderate love of this World and effeminate eaſe and Luxury, and requires all men to work and to be actually uſeful in the World, and particularly charges Chriſtians to Love all men as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, making this the Badge of Chriſtianity. Therefore they conclude that there ſhould not be ſuch an unequality among Chriſtians as there is. It is thought, they wiſh that Chriſtians would live ſome-what after the manner that the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> did by the direction of <hi>Lycurgus.</hi> Yet it muſt not be ſuppoſed that they expreſly require this of men, and that without it they'll never do good to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: But it is certain, they would at leaſt that men ſhewed that Moderation, Juſtice and Mercifulneſs that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58497:6"/>
their Natures require, and that Religion enjoyns; that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable abuſes were reformed, and that a due provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion were made for the helpleſs and innocent, and no man grieved or neglected, but all humanly treated and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly dealt with, as being, all, the Children of the ſame Father; that, in that ſenſe there might be <hi>ſome Equality</hi> among them, as the Apoſtle willeth it to be. Then would all men rejoyce, and the Nations would be right glad; the People would be at Peace and Amity, and the Earth would be full of tranquillity and order: Every one would have enough, and all might live comfortably; and Virtue and Piety would flouriſh every where in the World. Come then, Lord Jeſu! come quickly!</p>
                  <closer>Amen!</closer>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>VI: Sect.</hi> The inexcuſableneſs and folly of rejecting the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>efits which would accrue to the World, if things were ſo diſpoſed that <hi>Adepts</hi> were encouraged in ſome meaſure to communicate themſelves, and were put in a capacity to be Beneficial to Men.</head>
                  <p>TO ſhew the folly of rejecting the Benefits that would accrue to the World by theſe means, I need only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Reader to the Second Section, where thoſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages are ſummarily obſerved or hinted: That will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to help him to make all the Conſiderations that ought to be made on this Subject, if he will attend to it. And to ſhew the inexcuſableneſs of thoſe who reject theſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, we muſt only obſerve that the things which are here expreſly required, are nothing but what the Goſpel In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſibly demands, and what God expects from Men. So that to this caſe we may juſtly apply this Oracle, that it will be more tolerable for <hi>Sodom</hi> in the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than for thoſe who reſiſt good motions and deſpiſe the proferr'd Divine Favours, reject the Counſel of God againſt themſelves, and oppoſe the Eſtabliſhment of his Kingdom, and the execution of his Laws for the good of Men.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>The End of the Firſt Part.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:58497:7"/>
               <head>The Second Part of the Reſolution, containing an Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Expedients mentioned in the fifth Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the firſt Part, and ſhewing that they are Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and Reaſonable.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I. Section.</hi> The Occaſion of this Second Part.</head>
                  <p>NO doubt, thoſe who Laugh at the very name of a <hi>Philoſophers Stone,</hi> will accordingly deride the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients that have been mentioned, to encourage <hi>Adepts</hi> to communicate themſelves: Yet this mirth of the Scorners is not what we regard, and we do not now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne to go about to confute it: But it may be, even wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Perſons than thoſe, will think ſome of theſe Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents either<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtrange and obſcure, or unreaſonable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. I have therefore thought it neceſſary to explain at large, what has been ſaid compendiouſly in the fifth foregoing Section.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>II. Sect.</hi> An Explication of theſe words, <hi>It is thought,</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>depts <hi>wiſh that Chriſtians would live ſomewhat after the manner of the</hi> Lacedemonians.</head>
                  <p>IT is probable every Reader doth not know the manner how the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> lived, after the inſtutition of <hi>Lycurgus;</hi> and thoſe that know it, yet went to be reſolved what <hi>ſomewhat like this</hi> here implies: In ſumm, the uſe of Money<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was cried down among the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> (except the Iron Pieces, which being vile and of heavy Carriage, could occaſion no great Traſſick, which they thought was unneceſſary or rather inconſiſtent with a Tranquille Life) and the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> lived in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: They had a common Hall, where every one, even their Magiſtrates, met at a certain hour for their repaſts. This is as much as is here needful to be known of the <hi>Lacedemonians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58497:7"/>But, in the firſt place, it is not to be doubted, but Chriſtian <hi>Adepts</hi> would have Soveraign Magiſtrates live howſoever they like beſt. Chriſtianity inſpires a Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial awe for our Soveraigns, and declares the Anointed of the Lord to be Sacred, and charges Subjects to ſubmit themſelves to them, not only for wrath, but for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence-ſake.</p>
                  <p>As for inferiour Subjects, it is thought <hi>Adepts</hi> are of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion they might well live all in common, with relation to the poſſeſſion of the goods of the Earth and inferior Offices, if Souveraigns pleaſed ſo to order it. And this would be in ſome reſpect ſome what like the way of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> (tho' it ſhould alſo extreamly differ from it in many reſpects) if a Body of Chriſtians, excepting the higher among them, lived in Community together, much as they do in Colledges: And (being ſuppoſed to have, for their number, a proportionate quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Ground to what would fall to every ones ſhare, if the Earth was equally divided among men, not Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trically but according to the goodneſs of the Soil) if they were then all equally obliged to Till this portion of the Earth appointed to their ſhare, and only employ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to thoſe works which are abſolutely neceſſary for Life, and for the good of the Society; that would be that ſort of Life that is here meant, and that is in ſome reſpect compared to that of the <hi>Lacedemonians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to conceive this the better, and make it more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar, let us ſuppoſe, for inſtance, we have before us an Eſtate, of four hundred Pounds a year in the Country, to ſerve for a little Community, which we will divide into four ſmall Pariſhes adjoyning together, which will make a little Town. Let us ſuppoſe it ſo Peopled that three parts of four of the Land, one year with another may be abundantly ſufficient to keep its Inhabitants with all the neceſſaries of Life, and not much more. (If the Earth was equally divided, it would do that at the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> leaſt) The fourth part of the Eſtate, which was untouched, let
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58497:8"/>
us ſuppoſe it to be for the Rent and Maintenance of the Lord of the Mannour, and his Noble Family, who ſhall have nothing to do but to preſide over the Tenants, and ſee that they fall not out among themſelves, but that Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice be uprightly Adminiſtred among them. By the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, I mean all the Inhabitants of our Country Town, whom we ſuppoſe to hold the Land by the Grant, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Good will of the Lord of the Mannour: wherefore they have the care of the Husbanding of the whole Eſtate, but are to yield the fourth part of the Increaſe, and of their Labour, to their ſaid Lord and his Heirs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve for their own Maintenance, as has been ſaid, the three other parts.</p>
                  <p>The Lord of the Mannour, thus, ſhall be as it were a King among his Tenants; and (we may ſuppoſe) there ſhall be ſtanding Laws Solemnly Eſtabliſhed, according to which, as he comes to Age, he will take Oath to Govern them. And our little Town ſhall yearly chuſe three Members out of every Pariſh, for their Inferiour Magiſtrates, which, making the number of twelve, will, together, make as it were a Parliament, that ſhall Sit at ſet times, to Decide (with the Approbation and Confirmation of their Lord) of the Affairs of their little Community.</p>
                  <p>The Lord ſhall live in his Palace or Mannour-houſe, and ſhall have ſuch other Houſes and ſuch Servants, for himſelf and his Children and Family, as he ſhall think fit at firſt to appoint; and that ſhall be Eſtabliſhed in the ſtanding Laws, that it may ſo remain for the future,</p>
                  <p>The Tenants ſhall dwell in four Squares, or four great Houſes, that ſhall be like ſo many Colledges, each of which ſhall be a Pariſh. Let us imagine one of thoſe Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, for the Situation, like <hi>So-ho Square,</hi> or <hi>Red-Lyon Square</hi> in <hi>London.</hi> Let that ground in the middle of the Square, which in <hi>So-ho</hi> and <hi>Red-Lyon Square<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> is Railed in and kept for a Walk, be here employed to make a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Hall, and all the Appartments belonging to it, for our Tenants to meet together in, to make their Publick
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58497:8"/>
Devotion, to inſtruct their Children, and to take their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſts, and confer with one another. Let that Building be equally divided into two parts, exactly alike; the one part for the Men, and the other for the Women: Only let the great Hall, which ſhall be both a place for their Publick Devotion, and a place to Eat in, and to inſtruct their Children, be Common for the Men and Women; but let there be a great Curtain, as there is in ſome Schools, to be drawn from one end of the Hall to the other, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Hall exactly into two equal parts, length ways, to ſeperate the one part for the Men, and the other for the Women. Adjoyning to this Hall may be placed the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, the Kitchings, the Brewing and Baking Houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which to be double, the one for the Men, and the other for the Women. And all this Building muſt be contrived to be, together, Square; and it may all, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be called the Common Hall. It may be ſuppoſed to be Built of Brick, and Thatcht; and its height may be as that of a pretty high Hall in a Gentleman's Houſe. Let it be drawn within, and Paved with Brick. Let there be Stoves in the Hall; and good Brick Chimneys in the Kitchens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There may be ſuppoſed ſeveral Cupboards in the Wall of the Hall, round about the Hall; and drawers under the Tables, to put their Books of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and other Books, the Table-Cloths and Napkins and other Utenſils. And over the Hall, there may be Garrets, to keep Fruit in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> About this Publick Building, at the diſtance of the Breadth of an Ordinary Street, we may ſuppoſe there to be Built all along, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Buildings for the Inhabitants; a little Houſe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Family. Thoſe little Houſes ſhall be adjoyning one to another, and ſhall be Built about the Common Hall in four equal lines or Rowes, an equal row over-againſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Side of the great Four-ſquare Building or Common Hall. ſo that all together ſhall make an exact Square. Let all the dwelling-Houſes be exactly alike one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Let every Houſe have two little Rooms of a Floor,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58497:9"/>
and two little Cloſets to each Room. Let there be an Entry betwixt the two Rooms, and let the Stair-caſe be in the Entry. Let every Houſe be two Stories high. Let one of the ground-Rooms be a Parlour for the Maſter and Miſtreſs to Sit in when they are at Home, and to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Viſitants. The Cloſets may ſerve to put their Wood and Coals for their private Fires, and ſome to put their Trunks and hang their Garments in. The other ground-Room ſhall be to Lodge the Maid Servants in: Over that Room ſhall be the Chamber for the Maſter and Miſtreſs. And the other Chamber in the ſame Floor ſhall be the Nurſery for the Children. Over thoſe two Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, there ſhall be two little Garrets; the one for the Men Servants, and the other for a ſpare Bed. Let there be, in every one of thoſe Rooms, a little Chimney, that they may be Aired ſometimes. The Houſes ſhall be Thatched, and ſhall be as low as may conveniently be. In the Yard, which ſhall be of the length of the Houſe, but not ſo broad, there ſhall be the convenient Houſe or Eaſings, in one of the further corners of the Yard; and at the bottom of the Wall behind every one of thoſe, there ſhall be two ſmall Archesmade, to leave two low ſpaces voyd at the foot of the back wall to draw the Dung out, or let in the Swine to conſume it. Every Yard ſhall be divided from that of the next Neighbours by a ſmall Brick Wall. In the middle of the Wall of the Yard, that is length ways oppoſite to the Back of all the Houſe, there ſhall be a back door to go out at, ſometimes. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-againſt thoſe back doors, and thoſe Yards of the ſaid dwelling Houſes, at the diſtance of the breadth of a very wide Street, there ſhall be built (in four lines, ſquare, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that Back-ſide of the dwelling Houſes) other Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that ſhall be for Barns, for <hi>Magazines,</hi> for Shops to do the <hi>Mechanick</hi> Works in (except they may be placed about the Common Hall) for a Gaol, for Stables, Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, Sties, Hen-houſes, Waſh-houſes or Landries, Milk-Houſes, and Rooms to keep Cheeſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And about that,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58497:9"/>
at the diſtance of the breadth of an Ordinary Farmers Yard, ſhall be built four good Brick Walls, pretty high, which ſhall make a compleat ſquare, and ſhall wall in the Colledg or Pariſh. And in every Angle, or Corner, and Ending of theſe four Walls, there ſhall be a large Gate, to go out into the Fields.</p>
                  <p>I do not obſerve what other Conveniencies there may be in each Pariſh; for I do not deſigne to draw an exact Picture and they may be eaſily imagined. For inſtance, there may be a Garden walled about, and an Orchard in the ſpare Room near (or adjoyning to) the Magazines and Back-buildings; There may be alſo, if you will, twelve Poomps; One in every Street, which is four; and four at the back ſide of the Magazines and Barns, where ſhall be the general Yard for the Cattel; and four for the uſe of the Common Hall, two for the Men, and two for the Women. And, beſides the particular Houſes of Office in each Yard, there might be four Publick ones, two for each Sex. But theſe things, and the like, need not to be Particularized.</p>
                  <p>This then makes one Pariſh. And we adjoyn four near one another, to make a kind of Town, or Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the help and Service of one another. In theſe four Pariſhes we may ſuppoſe there is a ſufficient number of <hi>Carpenters, Maſons, Smiths, Plow-rights, Weavers, Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors,</hi> and the other like Trades abſolutely neceſſary to a Society, ſo that our little Town is like a Kingdom or a little World, which may ſubſiſt of it ſelf, and need not know what there is beyond its limits. As for Husbandry, we ſuppoſe all to be Husbandmen alike, beſides every one's own particular Trade or Calling. My meaning is, that every one ſhall have a Particular Handicraft or Vocation, to which he ſhall labour ſome days, or ſome hours of the day; but withal, every one alſo ſhall ſhare alike in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of the Husbandry, and there ſhall be ſet apart for that ſome days or ſome hours of the day. But with all their Work that they ſhall have to do (it they Work on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58497:10"/>
for themſelves, that is for the Inhabitants of the Town or the four Pariſhes, and they employ themſelves in no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther works but ſuch as are really neceſſary to a well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Society; our Pariſhioners and Townſmen and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men will find the Work they ſhall have to do very Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile and pleaſant. The Yoke will be eaſy, and the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den light. I reckon they ſhall have five hours to Work for the Publick every day, and one hour every one for himſelf; that's Six hours. Then there will be three hours every day ſet apart for Devotion and inſtruction in Religion; and three hours for Meals and Converſation: that's Six hours more; which makes twelve hours. We may allow one hour loſt in preparing for Work, and in putting up the Inſtruments after the Work, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let two hours be ſpent, towards the Evening, in a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Reading and hearing of Hiſtory, Law, and Phyſick, and ſuch like Studies in order, but let Romances be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly baniſhed. After that, two hours ſhall be allowed for Play or Recreation, or for every one to ſpend in his Houſe or in Viſits, as he pleaſes; That's hitherto, Five hours, beſides the firſt twelve. Then there remains ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hours for Sleep. Some certain days, to encourage the Youth, to recreate the Spirits, to train up Men in the exerciſe of Warr for the defenſive part, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there may be leſs time appointed for Work, and more for Play and Sport, ſuch as Fencing, Shooting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And, that the Youth be not unruly, there ſhall always be ſome of the Elder ſort obliged to be preſent with them: And none of different Sexes be allowed to play together; but Boys by themſelves, and Girles by themſelves. The firſt day of the Week ſhall be wholly a day of Reſt, Devotion, and Thankſ-giving. In each Pariſh, there ſhall be a School-maſter and a Divine, that all, from the youngeſt to the Oldeſt, may have due inſtruction. Daily alſo there ſhall be read among them, after Divine Service, ſome Portion of the Whole Duty of Man, and of ſuch other good Books, one after another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:58497:10"/>What has hitherto been ſaid, gives a general notion of the Chriſtian Life of our Country Town's men. We may now obſerve ſomthing more particularly, concerning, 1. Their Government, Marriages, and Servants; 2. Their Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; 3. Their Victuals; and Laſtly, Their Employment.</p>
                  <p>1. As to their Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It has already been ſaid, that as for their ſupream Government within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſuppoſing it to be ſo granted by the Souveraigns of the Countreys where they may be; that is as that of a King, and Parliament. And as for the inferiour Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among them, in their four Pariſhes, it may be like that of a Corporation; only it were well to change the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, as well as the Mayor, every Year; that every one may have his turn. They ſhall Marry, the Men ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, at ſix and twenty, and the Women at three and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or thereabouts. Every man ſhall have his Wife. And thoſe that ſhall not Marry three or four Years within the Term, as alſo thoſe that ſhall Marry ſo much before the time appointed, ſhall be liable to ſome Puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe that ſhall Marry without the knowledge and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Major part of the Governours; Or thoſe that ſhall commit Fornication and uncleaneſs, and thoſe that ſhall be convicted of Adultery, ſhall be Condemned to the higheſt Puniſhments. Thoſe that ſhall be convicted of Theft or Riot, ſhall be Condemned to Impriſonment for ſeveral Years, according to the demerit and noxiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Crime. And all thoſe that ſhall be Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Priſon, ſhall conſtantly Work ten hours at leaſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day at ſome Laborious Work, whilſt they remain there and continue the Publick's Slaves. They ſhall be Chained at both their Feet; but otherwiſe ſhall be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted humanely if they will faithfully Work, and if they ſhew themſelves to be Penitent; elſe they ſhall have due Correction, till they be perſuaded to do their duty. They ſhall be brought every morning to a Shop next the Gaol, where they ſhall Work. The Children ſhall live in their Parents or Gardians houſes, till they be ſeven years of Age.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58497:11"/>
Then they ſhall be diſpoſed of into other Men's Houſes, and if need be, into another Pariſh, to ſerve till they be Lawfully Married and have a Child, or till they be thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years old. Then they ſhall have a houſe allowed them of their own, with all neceſſaries and Servants; and they ſhall then be members of the Corporation, and ſhall be qualified, like others, for Offices.</p>
                  <p>The Maſters ſhall not be obliged to work ſo much as the Servants. And when they come to a certain Age, they ſhall be eaſed from the Laborious work. For, to do every thing according to Reaſon, the work muſt be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned to the Age, and Strength, and Dignity of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one. When they come to be Old, they ſhall be Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oured as Senatours, and ſhall ſerve only to give Counſel for the menagement of the Affairs, and to preſide and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſee every thing they can, and walk in the Streets, and keep good orders in the Pariſh when the reſt are in the Fields, or buſy at their Work.</p>
                  <p>There ſhall be no natural precedency among our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners, but that of Age. And if any deſerve to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed for ſome extraordinary Service, it ſhall be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his own Perſon, for his Life.</p>
                  <p>All Offices ſhall go by turn. There ſhall be Watchmen continually in the ſtreets of the Pariſh, Night and Day. And, that it may not be too tedious to any one, they ſhall be changed every four hours.</p>
                  <p>There ſhall be a kind of <hi>Corps-de-garde</hi> at every Gate of the Pariſh, where two Elderly Men or Women ſhall ſit as Centinels.</p>
                  <p>This ſuffices to hint what Government there might be in ſuch a conſtituted Pariſh. We may therfore proceed to ſay ſomwhat, In the 2 place, of their Rayment. That ſhall be exactly alike for all of equal Age and condition. And in ſhort, the Rayment of them all in general, ſhall be moſt plain, but as convenient as may be. But it muſt be as little chargable as is poſſible; for People may go plain, as the Quakers, and yet have coſtly Garments;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58497:11"/>
which is ridiculous. They ſhall have good Linnen, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too courſe nor too fine; and they ſhall have enough to be cleanly.</p>
                  <p>3. As for their Victuals, That ſhall be plain, but whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and they ſhall always have enough, but not to encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age Drunkneſs or Gluttony, and Wantonneſs. Therefore unneceſſary Sawces, and other things unneceſſary, as To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, and the like, ſhall not be allowed. For their Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, they may have Bread, Butter, and Cheeſe, and beſides that, Milk-porridge, or ſometime Water-gruel, or warm Milk, or Eggs boyled. For Dinner, they ſhall have freſh Meat every day; Boyled three days in the week, and Roſt three days, Roſt Fleſh one day, and Boyled another; the ſixth day of the Week, that is <hi>Friday,</hi> ſhall be a Faſt, and Fiſh or Eggs ſhall be eaten that day at the end of the Faſt. When they have Roſt-meat, they ſhall have Puddings Boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by themſelves: and the days they have their Meat boyled, inſtead of Puddings they ſhall have Broth; after the Meat, they may have Butter or Cheeſe. For Supper, they ſhall have the ſame they have for Breakfaſt. They ſhall have, for their ordinary uſe, good wholſom drink, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſhall have ſufficient. If it be thought fit, they may Brew alſo ſometime ſtrong drink, of which every one may have a reaſonable ſhare, as much as it ſhall be thought good and neceſſary. If they have more goods than is ſufficient for the Town and their Magazines, they may ſomtimes trade with the Men of the World: And the Mony they ſhall thus get, ſhall be for the Publick ſtock to buy, at ſomtimes, what ſhall be judged moſt neceſſary for their Society.</p>
                  <p>Pullets, Partridges, Small birds, and ſuch like means, (if they have any) ſhall be chiefly for the Sick and Infirm. For to do as we would be done to, is the law of Reaſon and the Dictate of the Wiſdom of God.</p>
                  <p>It ſhall not be permitted to have Pigeons, Geeſe, Swans<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For they deſtroy, and do hurt incomparably more than they are worth. For the ſame reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>here ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58497:12"/>
kept no more Dogs, Horſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than are uſeful and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, for if Men were content with what is neceſſary; and if the Earth was Husbanded to the beſt advantage for the neceſſities of life, there would be enough of all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and all Men might live happy. There remains on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now, 4. and laſtly, to ſay ſomewhat more of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. It has been already ſaid, that they ſhall Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelves about no other Work, but what is really convenient and neceſſary to a Chriſtian Society. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Painting, Ingraving, Weaving of Ribbon, or Lace, or the like Frivolous Arts, are blotted out of the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of our Manufactures. As for Muſick and dancing, I hold them indifferent. But if they be uſed, theſe cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be obſerved. 1. Neither of them muſt be a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or Employment of themſelves; but our Muſicians or Dancers muſt alſo have another Vocation more eſſentially neceſſary to the Society, and muſt practiſe their Muſick or Dance but at the ſpare-hours; and then they may be thought Worthy of ſome honour. 2. No Songs muſt be allowed on the Subjects of Love, nor drinking. 3. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of different Sexes muſt never be allowed to dance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and there muſt not be ſuffered changes of modes in Dances, no more then in Garments, nor muſt there be allowed a too great variety of dances, but only thoſe that are the moſt grave. If there was an Organ in every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Hall, I ſhould not diſallow of that. For Muſick is chearful, and chearfullneſs preſerves health. But the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent of the Major part muſt be followed, only it muſt be permitted to every one (that can expreſs himſelf) to give freely his Opinion, and every one muſt be patiently heard; and the Arguments deliberately weighed; and then no doubt, Reaſon will ever carryit. But in indifferent things, every one ought to be content to acquieſce. This is a ſerious digreſſion, which was not premeditated. But, as touching Muſick, there is none to be ſo much va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued as that of a good Voyce. And after all, the beſt Harmony is that of Concord and Love among Neighbours
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58497:12"/>
Brethren and fellow Chriſtians. <hi>By this,</hi> ſais our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>It ſhall be known if ye are my Diſciples.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt thing that ſhall be done in the morning (after our People have waſhed and are ready, and have been at their private Devotions, which ſhall all be done at Six of the Clock, there being an hour allowed for that and their dreſſing, being called up to riſe at five of the Clock at fartheſt; then juſt at ſix of the Clock, a Bell having tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) they ſhall repair to the Common Hall, where there ſhall be made a Publick Prayer, and one Chapter ſhall be read in the New Teſtament, after which every one ſhall receive the portion allowed for his Breakfaſt. After that every one alſo ſhall prepare for Work, and ſhall Work three or four hours, or more, as it ſhall be beſt determined Then the Bell ſhall toll again, and every one ſhall waſh and clean himſelf; and all things being diſpoſed of, and the laſt ſigne of the Bell being giving, all ſhall repair to the Hall again, where the whole Service ſhall be read, and after that, a portion of ſome Book of Devotion. Then will follow the Dinner, before and after which, Grace ſhall be ſaid. And after ſome Converſation after Dinner, there ſhall be Song a Spiritual Hymn, before they return to work. And thus they ſhall ſpend their time, much after the diviſion and deſignment of it, that has been mentioned. They may dine about one, and ſup about ſeven. Immediately alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Supper, the Service ſhall again be read. And at Night, the laſt thing that ſhall be done in Publick before they part, ſhallbe to Worſhip God by Prayer and Devotion. Women that are Nurſes, ſhallbe obliged in the day time to go now and then to their Children, which may be left ſeveral together in ſome place, to the care of ſome old Women or ſome young Maids, which ſhall take that charge by turns.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. III.</hi> How it would be poſſible for Chriſtian's to live much after that manner.</head>
                  <p>I do not doubt but that a thouſand Difficulties and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections will be raiſed againſt this manner of Living<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:58497:13"/>
but being ſatisfied they will be vain and frivolous one's, we'll ſuppoſe all reaſonable perſons, capable to diſcern their Vanity (and thoſe that are not reaſonable, will yield to no reaſon.) We will only anſwer ſome few, to ſerve for inſtances of the reſt.</p>
                  <p>It will firſt be objected, that Four Hundred a Year cannot ſuffice, to maintain our four Pariſhes according to the Deſcription, I have given of their way of living and likewiſe maintain the Landlord and his Family. I anſwer if that won't do, then allow more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I do not enter into that diſquiſition. But this I ſay, that if all men thus did work alike, and all poſſeſed the Earth alike, and buſied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about no imployment but what is neceſſary; they would all live as well at leaſt as I have repreſented our Pariſhoners to do. Then there is no more to be done, but to allow them ſuch an Eſtate for their number, as would fall to their ſhare if the Earth was equally divided among all men; that is, what will be abundantly ſufficient to keep them well, ſuppoſing they work moderately. For certainly God has made abundant proviſion for all his Creatures, and particullarly for thoſe that are Rational. Supp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e therefore what will do, and allow that, be it more or leſs.</p>
                  <p>2. Another Objection perhaps will be, that if Men have no more but juſt their ſhare of the things of this World, then 'twill be impoſſible to allow to every one of our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes ſuch convenient Houſes, ſuch Brick Walls, and ſuch other conveniences as we do. I Anſwer, That's a perfect miſtake: For, if all Men thus gave up themſelves alike to a moderate and neceſſary Labour, the World would be incomparably Richer than it is. And if our Pariſhes do ſo, and have proportionably their ſhare of the Earth, it will be the ſame thing, as far as it concerns us, as if it was ſo practiſed through out the whole World. Then, it muſt be confeſſed, Towns are not built in a day; but by degrees they arive to the greateſt perfection. As for our Brick walls, they are laſting, but not very Chargeable or diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58497:13"/>
to get, if every one would lend his help as he might. Many Garden-walls take up as much Ground and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Bricks, as ſhould do that which would ſerve to Wall in one of our Pariſhes. And if there was no Rent to Pay, excepting part of the Increaſe of a Super-abounding Eſtate, and if there went nothing in Superfluities and Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Luſts, all men might have dwelling Houſes, and Encloſures, and all the neceſſaries of Life.</p>
                  <p>3. There is another Objection to be made, <hi>viz.</hi> That tho' the Theory of this may ſeem probable, yet the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of it is abſolutely Impoſſible, becauſe men that have not been brought up to Work, will never be able to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject themſelves to it. I anſwer: Suppoſe that be a real difficulty, all that is to be done is this, Thou who haſt not been uſed to work, and yet approveſt of it, and now think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt it an equal duty; bring up thy Children to Work, and help to make up one of our Pariſhes: Conſecrate thy Children to God in it, and when thou dieſt, leave what thou haſt to the uſe of the Society where thou haſt cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to place thy Children, out of the Dangers and Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of this World: I mean, if ſuch a Society was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Eſtabliſhed. For I ſpeak only to ſhew the poſſibility of the thing. Therefore, ſuppoſe yet ſome of thy Children be already ſo far advanced to Age, that they can hardly be hereafter accuſtomed to Work, having been brought up Effeminately and Delicately. Why, then appoint them enough to be able to have all the Neceſſaries of Life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out working, and leave the remaining part of thy Eſtate for the uſe of our Pariſhes after thy deceaſe. There can be no difficulty in this, and if thou, and ſome other rich Men would think fit to do ſo, why could we not in time have as great a number of ſuch truely Religious Houſes of Laborious and good Chriſtians, as ſome Nations have of Irreligious Houſes, full of idle, and conſequently An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian folks?</p>
                  <p>But, laſtly, it will be ſaid, that would be a cumber to a Nation, and would do it no good; and therefore 'twill
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58497:14"/>
never be the intereſt of ſupream Governours to allow of it. I anſwer: it is eaſy to ſhew that all this is a miſtake. For would it do no good to a Nation to have a company of Young men Vertuouſly brought up, and ſome of them if ſuperiours pleaſed, trained from their Childhood in the diſcipline of Warr, to ſerve their Country in caſe of need For the ſupream Governours in caſe of Neceſſity, might require every one of our Pariſhes to furniſh them with an equal number of Young men to ſerve in the Warrs, till they came to a certain Age, and others were ſent in their room. And thoſe that ſhould ſtay at home, would no leſs advance their juſt undertakings with the Lord of Hoſts, by their devout and conſtant Prayers and holy Life; and by their Piety and examplary Virtue would draw a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon the Nation, and obtain of God to continue His Forbearance towards the great number of Sinners in the Land who deſerve ſevere Judgments. Beſides, Supream Governours might lay equal impoſitions upon our Pariſhes as upon other Eſtates; and ſuppoſe there ſhould be no uſe of Mony among them, Governours might receive the worth of the Taxes in Kind, in Corn, and Cattel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Why then ſhould they be more a cumber to a Nation, than a company of Gentlemen who have vaſt Eſtates, and are always idle, and often conſume their Goods in exceſs and Riot, and ſomtime conveigh their Revenues into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Land, where out of wantonneſs they chuſe to paſs part of their Life, without caring how fare their poor Country men?</p>
                  <p>But this pretended Objection, if any thing further need to be ſaid to it, ſhall be yet more fully refuted in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Section, where will be ſhewed the reaſonableneſs of this Collegiate Life of our Chriſtian Society.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. IV.</hi> That undoubtedly it would be moſt reaſonable and moſt Chriſtian like to follow that ſort of Life.</head>
                  <p>IF Men were calm and not Paſſionate; if they were ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and Juſt and not partial; and if they would rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58497:14"/>
conſider of things; they ſhould find that certainly it would be moſt reaſonable and moſt Chriſtian-like to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that ſort of Life. For,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. All men are of the ſame Family, and made of the ſame Blood;</item>
                     <item>2. The Law of Chriſtianity is, that we Love other men as well as our ſelves;</item>
                     <item>3. This would be a ſure way to make the generality of Men Happy;</item>
                     <item>4. It would be a great conveniency to the men of the World, that there ſhould be ſuch Societies eſtabliſhed;</item>
                     <item>5. To wiſh ill to ſo juſt a Conſtitution, argues much Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian partiality and Uncharitableneſs.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Now let us a little conſider all theſe Reaſons.</p>
                  <p>1. All Men are of the ſame Family, and made of the ſame Blood. Equality therefore, in a high degree, is the Law of our Natures; we are all made up of a Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Body and an immortal Spirit. All Mankind is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the ſame Mold, and they all bear the Image of the moſt High God: why then ſhould there be ſuch vaſt differences made betwixt them? All thoſe that are among us, where the Goſpel is Preached, are not they all capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of inſtruction and Salvation? Have they not all the ſame Baptiſm, the ſame Chriſtian hopes, the ſame Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, the ſame God and Father of us all? And thoſe who have the greateſt, shall they be denied the leaſt? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly we are all Brethren and equals, and all partake of the ſame common Nature.</p>
                  <p>Object. But perhaps you'll ſay, <hi>That notwithſtanding all Mankind are of the ſame Family, there has been always a great difference made betwixt Men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true. And no doubt God conſented it should be ſo, but certainly that was becauſe the World was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of that Natural, Pleaſant, and Loving way of living in equality and in Common. If <hi>Adam</hi> had not Sinned, there would not have been ſuch a vaſt difference made between Men; for it would have been alike Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58497:15"/>
to all to ſatisfie themſelves with the goodthings in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> But when Man was corrupt and become Wicked, it was thought fit that that ſhould happen to him which is the ordinary cauſe of the greateſt danger, grief and trouble; that is, unequality. Yet God doth not at all forbid, but rather wiſheth, if Men will be reaſonable, that they live in the ſame happy Eſtate again. But when I ſay, there ſhould not be in reaſon, ſuch a vaſt difference between men; 'tis plain I do not mean that there ſhould be no difference at all made. There muſt always be a diſtinction made betwixt Parents and Children, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Subjects, Old and Young, Maſters and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Virtuous Men and Criminous Perſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But, in general, that diſtinction muſt not be that the one ſhould Swim in the goods of the Earth, and the others ſhould Starve; but it is to conſiſt in this, that young People, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Children and Subjects reverence the Magiſtrates, their Parents, and Maſters, and thoſe that are Elder than themſelves; and the virtuous Men be Honoured and Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and Criminals puniſhed.</p>
                  <p>'Tis certain God has many times furthered Unequality among men, but it was becauſe they were unreaſonable, and it was a Puniſhment which in general He Inflicted upon the World. God is never the Author of Sin, but when men Sin wilfully, he ſometimes grants them their fooliſh deſires, and gives them up to their own reprobate mind: And then he permits evil to befal them, as himſelf ſays, <hi>Behold I frame evil againſt you:</hi> And accordingly, <hi>Evil came down from the Lord upon them.</hi> For, <hi>Shall there be evil in the City, and the Lord has not done it?</hi> Jere. 18. 11: Micah. 1. 12. Amos 3. 6. Therefore, tho' Unequality be an evil, it is not ſtrange if God has brought it upon fall'n Mankind; not that he forced it upon men, but, ſince men lived no longer in Common, but every one ſhifted for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, God was the maſter to make thoſe, whom He pleaſed, to proſper. They, none of 'em, deſerved any of God's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours; therefore He might beſtow them if He would, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58497:15"/>
deny them to whom He pleaſed. That may ſerve for a full anſwer to what may be objected from the difference which God made betwixt <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> and the <hi>Jewes</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> God is the Maſter of the World, and He may diſpenſe His Graces as it ſeemeth beſt to His Godly Wiſdom. But Men depend one of another; and they are tyed to the Laws which God has given them. And thoſe are the Laws of their Nature, and the Laws of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation. We have taken a view of the firſt. Now let us conſider the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>2. The Law of Chriſtianity is, that we love other men as our ſelves, Chriſt calls this <hi>His Beloved Commandment.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſais, <hi>wethout this Love, a man is nothing,</hi> Now, can we reaſonably think we love other men as our ſelves, when we are at eaſe and others in trouble; when we take our reſt, and others labour ſore; when we have all delicacies, and others are half ſtarved; when we, who perhaps leaſt deſerve it, are Honoured, and expect to be ſo, and we depreſs and contemn other men? If this be Chriſtianity, the Devi is the rareſt Chriſtian imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: But men are reſolved to blind their own ſelves. Whatever be ſaid, they will put black for white, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ſweet; they have always don ſo, and 'tis to be feared they always will. (Nevertheleſs God thinks it fit their Duty ſhould be repreſented them, if it be only to ſerve for a Teſtimony againſt them, if they will not let it ſerve to milder purpoſes. How can we ſay we love other men as our ſelves, when we make ſuch differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and us? We put almoſt as great a difference between ſomemen and ſome other men, as between ſome men and a Beaſt; when it may be the Perſons we deſpiſe, in the Sight of God are the beſt and in the higheſt eſteem. Otherwiſe, men are all alike, like Counters made of the ſame Metal. But ſure we think poor men are of another kind, and were born to be abuſed, and uſed like Dogs. Alaſs, how came he to be Poor, and thou to be Rich? Probably, thro' Unjuſtice and Oppreſſion; for Innocence
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58497:16"/>
is oppreſt, and Vice flourisheth in the World. Poſſibly, his Anceſter was an honeſt, harmleſs man, and was rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of all, by the Knavery of others; and thy great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grand-Father perhaps was the Thief, and thus thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeſt the fruit of his iniquity: Much good may it do thee. What haſt thou gained thereby? Vanity and Vexation: The Poor in his ſtraights crieth to Heaven, and God abominates thee and thy ways, and will judge thee for thy Sin. Thou haſt been brought up delicately and effeminately, and art not uſed to work; if thy Eſtate should fail thee, thou knoweſt not how to get thy living: Therefore thou dreadeſt the thoughts of that, and wouldſt be ready to pawn thy Soul, to ſupply thy luſts and thy ſuper-induced and ſuperfluous neceſſities; thou art every moment afraid to loſe thy Money, for that's truly thy hope and thy confidence, O thou Idolater! <hi>There is no Peace, no Tranquillity for thee,</hi> ſaith God; and how canſt thou have peace, when the exceſs of thy abundance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth ſo many, thy fellow Creatures. to want and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish, and that ſtirs them to envy thee, and wish thee ill. Whereas,</p>
                  <p>3. If there was an Equality among men, that would be a ſure way to make the generality of men happy. There would be no Thieves then as there is now, for there would be no occaſion to Steal, nor ſuch temptations to Sin, as now there is. All men would have enough, and would Bleſs, and Help, and Comfort one another. Sweet Bleſſed Life! And would not that be a Chriſtian Conſtitution? A ſufficient proviſion would be made for all men; and no man should die with that grief to ſee that he leaves his poor Children unprovided for; every one should take moderate pains; but no honeſt man should be a ſlave. But conſider now how ſorely a vaſt number La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, from morning till night, and can ſcarce get half a Belly full of Meat, for themſelves and their wretched Family: Regard what miſerable Victuals they feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Bread as black as Soot, and heavy as Lead, and, with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58497:16"/>
this, often, unwholſom water to diſgeſt it; they have not a piece of Flesh-meat once in an Age, but often eat what ſome Dogs would not touch, when they ſee daily others fare ſumptuouſly. Can ſuch peoples Lives be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable? Can they be healthful? Can we be ſaid to love them as our ſelves? See how miſerable they are, when they linger with Sickneſs: They want ſometimes Rags to cover them; and ſcarce have Shoes to go dry foot. When they burn with a Feavour, there's no Surgeon to come to them; when they are ſcorched with thirſt, and raving for want of Sleep, there's no Phyſitian will come to adviſe them, and they die miſerably in torment. But will not God require it?</p>
                  <p>If it go not ſo hard with a great number of the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſort of Men; yet how many a one Threſhes all day for Six pence, when it may be he has above Six ſmall Children to provide for? But which is much more De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable, what poor Proviſion is there made for their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction? Alaſs, the generality of them have no more E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation than brute Beaſts; they are never taught what the Goſpel is, or what the Chriſtian Religion means; and they are made to know no more reaſons to believe it, than to believe the <hi>Alcoran.</hi> Indeed what means can they have of Inſtruction, as things are carried now? Do we not then neglect the Souls of Poor Men, for which Chriſt thought not too much to Die? For alaſs, it may be the Poor Fathers and Mothers know nothing themſelves, and never ſo much as learned to Read And beſides, when they leave Work, they are tired and want reſt; yet they have their Children to Feed, and the houſe-work yet to do; and it may be they have not one of their Children big enough to help them. Now, if thou wouldeſt but conſider it, what Miſerable and Bruitiſh Life is that they lead! Poverty ordinarily makes thoſe weak Chriſtians ungentle and Peeviſh, always croſs and angry; and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them to live moſt unchriſtianly, and inſtead of Loving and Comforting, continually to Brawl and Quarrel, and ſpight and hate one another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:58497:17"/>But in our Chriſtian Community, the work would be Eaſy; the Victuals would be ready got for them that Work; they ſhould be wholſom, and there would be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; Every Family might have both Men and Women Servants; and every perſon might live chearfully and Comfortably. And, which is the moſt conſiderable of all, there would be ſufficient Proviſion made for the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Soul to Eternal Life.</p>
                  <p>How many People ſeldom or never go to Church, out of Bruitiſhneſs and want of Senſe of Religion, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time becauſe they are taken no notice of and there is no room for them in the Church, particularly in great Towns. But in our Pariſhes no Body could be abſent from Publick Worſhip, but it might eaſily be obſerved and Remedied.</p>
                  <p>As concerning this Periſhable Life, there is one great Evil muſt not be paſſed by, tho' it cannot be noted but to the ſhame of Chriſtians, or indeed of Men. The Poor have not only all the difficulty in the World to live, when they have Youth and Strength; but they are alſo neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to Slave themſelves all their Life, and to Toil and Drudge in their Old and Feeble Age, and Work hard to the laſt minute they Breath, as if they had never done any thing for the Society. But it would not be ſo, if there was an equality among men.</p>
                  <p>But thou wilt ſay; Equality has alſo its inconveniences. Rich and Gay Attire muſt then be layd aſide, as alſo good Fellowſhip, and the quinteſſence of the delights of Life. And were it not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to renounce our Rich Wines, our Sweet Perfumes, our Jewels, and Pictures, our Coaches, and Furniture, and all the Pleaſures and Conveniences in the World? And muſt our Children be brought up, to be Servants to thoſe we have been uſed to deſpiſe and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand?</p>
                  <p>I Anſwer, This Objection utterly ſavoureth of the things of men, and not of the things which be of God. What, hadſt thou rather keep thy Gay Attire, than relieve the World from Slavery and Miſery? Where is thy Temperance
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58497:17"/>
and Moderation? If Equality has no other incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience than to oblige men to uſe neat, but modeſt and decent Garments, the inconveniences of it are not great. (<hi>Deſpiſe ye the Church of God, and ſhame them that have not?</hi>) But what reaſon is there thou ſhouldſt abound in Superſluities, and others ſhould want Neceſſaries? And what inconvenience is that to oblige thee not to get a Surfeit, but to teach thee Temperance, and learn thee to take care of thy Health? God forbids thee no delights but ſuch as are Foolish and not neceſſary, or that are hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to thy ſelf and others, or that are unnatural and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure. What neceſſity is there for thy Strange Wines, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes, and Jewels? There is not any, no more than for thy Pictures, and ſuch other like Pageantries and Foppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. And why should not thy Children ſerve others, as well as other Peoples Children ſerve thee? If they live, their turn will come to be ſerved themſelves. And why should they not ſerve others, if they are willing others should ſerve them one day?</p>
                  <p>This we ſpeak, not as if it was Lawful to trouble or reſiſt the Conſtitution that is in the World, ſince men shift for themſelves and have left off to live in common; which tho' we do not think to be ſo well nor ſo reaſonable, yet being Eſtabliſhed, it muſt be Sacredly complyed with, and muſt not be at all altered, except thoſe who, thro'-Gods Providence, are in Authority, were pleaſed in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to order it. But what we urge all along<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is only to ſhew what in it ſelf would be moſt reaſonable.</p>
                  <p>We may repreſent theſe reaſons to thoſe that are Rich and alſo to thoſe that are in Authority, eſpecially being Chriſtians; becauſe, if they do not altogether order this, they may hereafter order ſomthing equivalent to it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for the Neceſſities and Inſtruction of the Poor, and ſo aiming at ſome ſort of equality, eſpecially if <hi>Adepts</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated themſelves to ſome of them. And if they ſhould build and endow ſome ſuch Houſes in Community, as that I have deſcribed; it might perhaps induce ſome <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>depts</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:58497:18"/>
to enable them to build more, and do a greater good. However, by what has been ſaid it appears theſe Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings would not prove uſeleſs; and in the mean time they cannot reaſonably be thought impertinent or hurtful. For as they authorize nothing but what is agreeable to order and is for the good of every Man, and the quiet and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of the World<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo they declare that <hi>Adepts</hi> do not abſolutly require ſuch a perfect Reformation, to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with to communicate themſelves to Men; as we ſhall briefly ſee in the next Section. Yet,</p>
                  <p>4. It would be a great Conveniency to the Men of the World, if there were ſuch Societies endowed and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, as there are Convents and Monaſteries in other Countries. It might be a good Nurſery to bring up Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in, and inure them to Work, before they came to their Eſtates and to be their own Maſters. It is a good Policy of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and of ſeveral among the <hi>Germans,</hi> to make all their Children Work and learn a Trade. It makes them ſtronger, and of a more healthful Conſtitution. And beſides, if afterwards their Eſtates ſhould happen to fail them; they would know how to get their Livelyhood; without depending on others, being uſed to Labour. They would be fit to Travel throughout the World, and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Chriſtianity, when the day of Viſitation, appointed by God, ſhould come. If there were ſuch Houſes, it may be ſome <hi>Adepts</hi> would repair to them, to live there, and be Members of the Corporation; which they would ſufficiently enrich, with the Portion they would bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with them. Finally, ſuch Societies would be alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry convenient, for Gentlemen, there to diſpoſe of their Younger Children, as they do in Religious Houſes in ſome Countries.</p>
                  <p>5. And Laſtly, It is ſelf-evident that to wiſh ill to ſo Juſt a Conſtitution, argues much unchriſtian Partiality and uncharitableneſs. It ſhews men to be very ſelfiſh and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, and not to care what becomes of other Men, ſo they fare but well themſelves every day. Thus many that call
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58497:18"/>
themſelves Chriſtians (being born in that part of the World where the Chriſtian Religion is Profeſſed, yet) have nothing of Chriſtianity in them, altho' they make their boaſt of the Name of Chriſt, and pretend externally a mighty Zeal for Chriſtianity and the Speculations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and perhaps are learned in the Sacred Languages and it may be in the writtings of the Fathers: Yet theſe very men, had they lived in the time of Chriſt and His Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and heard them diſcourſe concerning Love, and its Duties, would, no doubt, have fiercely oppoſed both the Maſter and the Diſciples, and been ready to cry, <hi>Away with'em, Crucify, Crucify.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is certain, in Scripture, all are required to work, and Chriſtians are commanded to bear one anothers Burdens, and not to have the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Lord of Glory, with reſpect of Perſons. Nay the Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of plating the Hair, and wearing of Gold, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, are expreſly forbidden. But 'tis not of Late, that Chriſtians ſeem to have forgot all thoſe things. They bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie themſelves about wrangling in obſcure Queſtions and Speculative matters, and deſpiſe that which is plain, and indiſputable, and which tends to Practice and a Holy Life, (which is the Summ and Eſſence, the End and Intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the Goſpel) and they neglect and paſs by the weighty matters, inward Purity, Juſtice and Mercifull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Thus they deal with Religion: but no ſhifts will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with God. He will Judge all men according to the Goſpel. And then, many that call themſelves Chriſtians, ſhall not paſs for ſuch. Thou wouldeſt be willing, it ſeems, to be a Chriſtian, ſo thou mighteſt do what thou likeſt, and didſt juſt obey, of what Chriſt commands, that which thou wert pleaſed. Rare Chriſtian! who refuſeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt for his Maſter, and thinks he knows beſt what ought to be preſcribed and practiſed.</p>
                  <p>It is certain, they that contradict the plain tendency of the Goſpel, and that which is agreeable to the Spirit of Chriſt, and is repreſented to us as the Eſſence of Religion,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58497:19"/>
as the Loving other Men as our ſelves, indiſputably is; they are plainly Antichriſtians; they evidently oppoſe the Kingdom of Chriſt, Fight againſt God, and reſiſt His will, moſt certainly do the work of the Devil, and are abſolutely unfit and unqualified for Salvation.</p>
                  <p>There is no other Religion wherin men may be Saved, but that which Chriſt has taught. Nor can we ſhew that we are Sincerely of that Religion of His, but by keeping His Commands. Now has He not charged us by His Meſſengers, that we ſhould not ſet our affections on the things of this world; That we ſhould renounce all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vanities; that we should uſe this world without abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it; And that if need be, we should forſake all for His Sake? But what appearance is there that men are in that Religious diſpoſition, and that they would reſigne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the utmoſt ſufferings for Chriſt; if now for His Sake they will not ſo much as ſubmit to abſtaine from Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities and from Partiality, to Love other men equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with themſelves?</p>
                  <p>What has been ſaid is abundantly ſufficient to evince, that ſuch a Community as has been mentioned, is both poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and reaſonable; and that it would be moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> like to follow that ſort of Life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. V.</hi> That yet <hi>Adepts</hi> cannot be thought to require ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſo much, for if they pleaſed, they might eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Men to an abſolute neceſſity to do ſo.</head>
                  <p>THat <hi>Adepts</hi> cannot be thought to require expreſly ſo much of Men, is plain; becauſe if they would, they might oblige all mankind to live much after the manner we have deſcribed, that is, for the greateſt part of Men, to work alike, and Live in Common. For, to that End, they need but publish their Art to the world. Then, when every Body knows how to make eaſily infinite quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Gold and Silver, Mony muſt needs grow vile and good for nothing; no Body will ſlave for wages, and all will be Rich alike, new diviſions being neceſſary to be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58497:19"/>
made. For thoſe that have Lands, not knowing how to work, will be obliged to quit the greateſt part of their Eſtates to thoſe that will take the care to till them. But, as in the Apoſtolick times it was approved that Chriſtians should Live in Common, but it was not expreſly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; ſo <hi>Adepts</hi> likewiſe prefer that way of Living, but they do not force men to follow it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. VI.</hi> That in general, they would undoubtedly require of men nothing but Secrecy and Fidelity, Reaſon and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, Juſtice and Mercifulneſs; and that 'tis not to be doubted, could they be aſſured of theſe, they would be ready to communicate themſelves, under ſome juſt limitations.</head>
                  <p>THere is no reaſon to doubt, (for thoſe that believe there are <hi>Adepts</hi> in the world, and that they are Good and Pious men, who live in the Fear of God, and heartily wish well to Mankind) but that all that <hi>Adepts</hi> require, is, 1. that they may be ſecure from the Violence and wickedneſs of Men; and, 2. that they may be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that thoſe they shall Communicate themſelves to, will be ruled by reaſon and the Fear of God, and will do good (according to the <hi>Adepts</hi> directions) and not Miſchief with the <hi>Elixir.</hi> Theſe are the juſt limitations, under which undoubtedly, they would freely Communicate them ſelves for the good of a People. They therefore indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſibly require Juſtice and Mercifullneſs, Reaſon and Moderation, Secreſy and Fidelity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. VII.</hi> What this Condition, more particularly, may be ſuppoſed, for inſtance, to Imply.</head>
                  <p>THe above<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> mentioned conditions may be thought to Imply, for inſtance, thoſe or the like, particulars: That ſelfish worldly deſigns may be made (as much as poſſible) to be layd aſide, and the good of all Men particularly reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; that a Proviſion may be made that the poor may live more comfortably, and be better inſtructed; that a fixed rate may be Publickly ſet, from time to time, to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58497:20"/>
moſt things that are Sold, to avoyd as much as is poſſible Cheating and Lying in Buying and Selling; That the abuſes of Courts, and all unreaſonable cuſtoms there may be reformed; that Phyſitians and Lawyers, as well as Divines, may have ſet ſtipends, that Juſtice and Phyſick may be Common and diſpenced <hi>Gratis</hi> to all Men; that ſome Children may be brought up (in houſes founded for that purpoſe) to be ſent into ſeveral places, to propagate the Goſpel; That Phyſitians Children, and thoſe of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and Lawyers, and alſo thoſe of Souldiers be brought up at the charge of the Publick (that the Fathers may have no occaſion to be greedy of gain, and have no other care incumbent upon them than the Improvement of their Calling and the aſſiduous diſcharge of their Duty; And that the ſaid Children be made uſe of for the Service of the Country, in either of thoſe Callings, and be Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red according to their Capacities and deſerts; That how many mercenary Souldiers ſoever there be employed, to ſupply the defect of the Militia, none have leſs then one Shilling a day actually in mony, but that none be kept in Idleneſs, but be employed all day in ſome Work, for the good of the Publick, and be carefully inſtructed in Religion, and every one of them be bound to Marry at a certain Age; that thoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> among them and Seamen, that ſhall be convicted to be habitual prophane Swearers, have their Tongue bore through with a hot Iron; That Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezans, Coiners and Thieves be kept in a Bridewell all their Life, to work for the Publick; That moſt ſevere Puniſhments be determined to be indiſpenſibly inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Fornicators and Adulterers; That better Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be made than there is, that Scholers be carefully brought up and exerciſed in Devotion and Piety, as well as in human Learning; That all Gaming for mony, change of Modes in Clothes, Rich Garments and Furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and all Superfluities and vain and unneceſſary Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences be hinder'd by moſt ſevere Penalties, and eſpecially drinking in Tippling-Houſes, none of that Nature being
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58497:20"/>
allowed, but only a few Inns for Travellers; That Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Practical Diſcourſes, ſuch as the Book called <hi>The Whole-Duty of Man</hi> and the like approved Books concerning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be read conſtantly in the afternoon, in every Church all the Year; And that every Church be ſo diſpoſed; that all thoſe that Pariſh there, may have room; That the Perſon to whom any <hi>Adept</hi> may communicate himſelf, will bind himſelf to communicate the Secret to no body elſe, but will leave that wholly to the <hi>Adepts</hi> choice; and in fine, that the greateſt Zeal ſhall conſiſt in uſing force and the Arm of Power, not againſt Speculative Errours, but againſt Vices and known Sins. For thoſe who have a real reſpect for the Scriptures, and underſtand them as well as they can, may be Innocent and honeſt Men, tho' they err. No Violence then ought to be offered to Conſcience. And to avoyd Stumbling-blocks and put no Stone of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in our Brethren's way, and to further Concord, Peace and Amity, nothing ſhould be required for Union but what is Scriptural. Elſe we make our ſelves wiſer than the Spirit of God that dictated the Scriptures, and we run the hazard to vary from his Aſſertions, and thwart his Deſigns</p>
                  <p>It is certain, if there are <hi>Adepts</hi> in the World, God will never permit them to communicate themſelves to any Nation except that People be reformed and become ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually Righteous and Juſt; which it will never generally be, if moſt of the above mentioned particulars, or the like, be not obſerved and provided for, which might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be, and would be infallibly of unexpreſſible advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to Human Society.</p>
                  <p>If, for inſtance, Phyſitians, Lawyers and Souldiers were, as well as Divines, provided for, for their Lives; if their Children were taken off of their hands as ſoon as born and brought up in houſes and by perſons hired for that purpoſe, and if their Widows were to preſide over theſe Houſes, and had a ſet annuity allowed them for life: what need were there that either Phyſitians or Lawyers,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58497:21"/>
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould have large Salaries; or what occaſion were there that they ſhould have that greedineſs after gain that makes them both ſlight and Injure the poor and oppreſs the Rich, which is one of the greateſt diſorders and the greateſt grievances? To maintain the ſaid Widows and Children, the third part of the Salaries that otherwiſe ſhould be appointed to the men of the ſaid ſeveral Callings, might yearly be reſerved for that uſe, and all manner of Goods or Eſtate that ſhould appear to belong to them, might be appropriated to the ſame after their Deceaſe, the Survivers being inſpecters over that Buſineſs.</p>
                  <p>If every perſon of what quality and Eſtate ſoever was obliged to follow ſome Employment or other, for the good of the Publick, how much more eaſy would all things be to the Society than now they are, eſpecially if all Superfluities and unneceſſary expences were alſo cut off and hindered?</p>
                  <p>Now, why could not Perſons of Quality and Eſtate be bound to bring up their Children in all ſorts of Learning, and thoſe obliged at a certain age to exerciſe ſome Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Gratis</hi> for the Publick, either in the Profeſſion of Divinity, Law, Phyſick, or in the Army?</p>
                  <p>And why could not all Superfluous expences be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and all the occaſions of them be cut off? There is nothing occaſions unneceſſary Expences more than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary Arts, unneceſſary Ornaments in Clothes and Furniture, and unneceſſary Eating and Drinking.</p>
                  <p>It is evident the former might eaſily be remedied, and why could not there a Law be enacted, on the greateſt Penalties, regulating our Tables, and forbidding any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to Eate or Drink together ſave at the uſual meals in the day, Dinner and Supper, and each of theſe meals not to laſt above the ſpace of one hour?</p>
                  <p>If all the occaſions of Superfluous Expences were cut off, we might be able to give a good price for all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary works made in the Nation; to pay well all work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>people, to ſet all the Poor a work, that are able to work
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58497:21"/>
(if a Private man and an ordinary Citizen, as Mr. <hi>F.</hi> with good management was able to ſet ſo many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands a work, as is to be ſeen in his Life; what could not a Parliament, what could not a Nation do; are we then excuſable if any want among us?) to make ſufficient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions for the Sick and Old, for Children and Widows; and in fine, to pay all Subſidies eaſily and chearfully.</p>
                  <p>For whereas a great part of a Princes Revenues are founded upon the Extravagant Expences of his Subjects, there might be an equal Poll, proportionably to every ones ability, and likewiſe an equal Tax yearly eſtabliſht in lieu thereof,</p>
                  <p>If things were ſo ordered, there would not be ſo many occaſions of Sin as now there is, and every one in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would live well and Comfortably.</p>
                  <p>All Workmen and Servants might then (there being leſs work to do) find an hour in the day to Pray and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in Publick, Morning and Evening; and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly, would thereby draw God's Bleſſing on their Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and themſelves, and on the whole People, if God's Service was ſtricktly kept.</p>
                  <p>To live Luxuriouſly is but a Cuſtom: If it was broke off, no Body would miſs it, and evidently it would be of infinite advantage to the Society that it were ſo. If Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren was uſed from their Infancy to little elſe than Bread and Water, had ſufficiently of that for the Neceſſities of Nature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſaw all along no body before them uſe other nouriſhment; they'd never think that inſufficient nor would ever want nor deſire other, but in all probability ſhould enjoy health and ſtrength both of Body and Mind, better than all other Men How eaſily then might men earn more than ſhould anſwer all the Neceſſaries of Nature, if things were Rightly menaged!</p>
                  <p>Many Poor Families complain of having too great a number of Children to provide for; many Fathers and Mothers go with ſorrow to the Grave, ſeeing no Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made for the Maintenance of their numerous Family
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58497:22"/>
nor for the bringing of them up in the fear of God; and there are many perſons in the World that paſs their Lives in perplexity and diſcontent, and in the want of many things, or in diſhoneſt and unlawful courſes to get that which they want: Whence proceeds all this Evil? even from ſuperinduced neceſſaries, from a cuſtom of being uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, and deſiring them more inordinately than thoſe things which are actually neceſſary. The number of People would be no cumber, to a Land, if there was no Pride nor Luxury in the World.</p>
                  <p>If the Nation made a Fund to hire Houſes and Servants to receive and bring up all the Children that ſhould be brought to them: ſuppoſe there was never ſo many brought, the Publick certainly would loſe nothing by 'em, if the ſaid Children was uſed all along to have no more than would reaſonably ſuffice Nature, and if they was kept all their Life to work moderately for the Publick. They would paſs their lives without care, want or Perplexity; and they might be of infinite uſe to a Nation: And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as now there are many Perſons that are burdenſome and offenſive to it, there would be none if a right Method was taken. How happy might Princes make their People, if there was opportunity to conſider and effect all theſe things! If Parliaments was called to ſit conſtantly one half of the Year, they might in time have the oppertunity to find Remedies to all thoſe diſorders, that are a ſhame to the Profeſſours of Chriſtianity, and which, no doubt, incenſe God Almighty's Wrath againſt us. May God in His in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Mercy inſpire every one in his Station with what he is to do, and what every one in particular ſhall anſwer for at the great Day of Judgment!</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. VIII.</hi> The Aſſurance which has been intimated that Princes might give.</head>
                  <p>WHat inconvenience would there be, if a Prince, Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious for Piety and Juſtice as well as Valour, did take a Publick and SolemnOath (beſides that of his Inſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58497:22"/>
that, if there are <hi>Adepts</hi> in the world, and if any of them communicate himſelf to him; he will Religiouſly obſerve thoſe above-mentioned, or the like conditions? It were to be wiſhed that all the Princes in the World would agree to do this. That would Infallibly be a means to perſwade <hi>Adepts,</hi> if there are ſuch, to communicate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if God did then think ſit to permit it. And, if there are <hi>Adepts</hi> (as there is reaſon to believe there is) would the Lord might be pleaſed to prepare their Way, and in His own good time to ſend them, for the relief of Men, and chiefly for the Honour of His Great Name, and the advancement of Piety, Holineſs and Virtue!</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. IX.</hi> What Great men might reaſonably do, in order to obtain the <hi>Elixir</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT would be ſo great an Advantage to men to enjoy the Benefits of the <hi>Elixir,</hi> that no reaſonable means to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it ſhould in reaſon be neglected. And there is no Great Man but might put in for it, ſuppoſing he be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous for his Probity and Underſtanding, as well as for his Riches For, that which will invite <hi>Adepts</hi> is, 1. <hi>Virtue,</hi> 2. <hi>Secrecy,</hi> 3. <hi>An Honourable eſteem, and an Ingenuous ſearch and ſtudy of their Art;</hi> And Laſtly, <hi>The being in a Capacity of doing much good with the</hi> Elixir.</p>
                  <p>1. <hi>Virtue.</hi> Be thy Riches never ſo great, and thy deſires of the <hi>Elixir</hi> ſo inordinate as to make thee ſpend unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably in ſearch of it, and uſe never ſo many means to that end; thou ſhalt never proſper, if thou beeſt not Virtuous. Reaſon, and unanimouſly all the Writtings of <hi>Adepts</hi> warrant it: God then will never bleſs thy Work, nor enlighten thy Mind, nor ſend <hi>Adepts</hi> to thee. A <hi>Cherub</hi> with a Flame of Fire ſtands at the Gate of <hi>Eden,</hi> to barr all the wicked from it. If they was entruſted with the <hi>Elixir,</hi> they would turn the World upſide down, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſh it with Iniquity and Oppreſſion, and fill the world with Scandal. If thou beeſt therefore a Swearer, or a Drunkard, an Effeminate, or an Unjuſt Perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58497:23"/>
no thoughts of finding the <hi>Elixir;</hi> for infallibly thou wilt never get it.</p>
                  <p>2. <hi>Secrecy.</hi> Tho' thou wert Virtucus thy ſelf, yet if thou beeſt not ſecret in the Superlative degree, thou canſt not have the <hi>Elixir;</hi> for thy want of Secrecy might betray it into the hand of other Perſons that perhaps ſhould not be virtuous, and would make an ill uſe of it. And what greater miſchief can there be, than to betray thoſe <hi>Arcana</hi> of the Almighty, which are neceſſary to be kept ſecret for the preſervation of Mankind?</p>
                  <p>3. <hi>An Honourable eſteem, and an Ingenuous Search and Study of the Art.</hi> The <hi>Elixir</hi> will not ſeek the Scorners; and the Honny will never be for the <hi>Drones.</hi> It is affirmed an <hi>Adebt</hi> once thought fit to convince an incredulous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by giving him a ſmall particle of the <hi>Stone,</hi> and telling him how he might make projection of it at his leiſure; but it was never known that an <hi>Adept</hi> communicated the ſecret to a deſpiſer of the Art. But that is remarkable, which I have heard a Wiſe and Grave man tell: A learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſon, about fourty years ſince, had conceived a mighty contempt and averſion for the <hi>Hermetik</hi> Art, and uſed for ſeveral years, whenever he heard ſpeak of it, to cry it down w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h Indignation as Fooliſh and Falſe. At laſt, he took a reſolution to read the Books that treat of the <hi>Stone,</hi> that he might the better be able to expoſe the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of it: But inſtead of that, in reading, he diſcovered the way to make the <hi>Elixir;</hi> ſome time after, fell to work, and actually made it, and got a very large quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of it. Afterwards, feeling Death near, he ſent in haſte for Mr. <hi>H.</hi> (the perſon that related this) who was his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Friend and a very Learned and Good Man; but not being able to come till ſome days after, all that the <hi>Adept</hi> could tell him was that he had deſigned to reveal his Secret to him by word of mouth, and that what he delivered to him, was the <hi>Powder of Projection,</hi> which he cauſed then to be given him. Howbeit, neither Mr. <hi>H.</hi> nor the <hi>Adepts</hi> Widow, who both made trial of it many
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58497:23"/>
times, could ever make Projection with it; and ſo, not knowing what to do therewith, did neglect it, and in fine, let it be ſcattered and loſt. I cannot ſtill but be wail the loſs; for it was their unskilfulneſs hindred the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. But, in ſhort, who will obtain the <hi>Elixir</hi> muſt work for it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laſtly,</hi> If a Perſon that is Eminent for Probity and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy, and that is a lover of the Art, be alſo in a ſtation to be able to do much good; that will be all the induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment poſſible to move an <hi>Adept</hi> to communicate himſelf to him. <hi>Irenaeus Philalethes</hi> came to <hi>London</hi> a purpoſe to impart the Art to the Honourable Mr. <hi>B.</hi> who undoubtedly might have done a great deal of good with it, doing much good with what he had, and, beſides his good diſpoſition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a capacity to render great ſervices to the Publick by reaſon of his quality and fortune, his Credit and I ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. But that Honourable Perſon, who had ſuch Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and acquired accompliſhments, and was ſo well qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified for Philoſophy, and extremely deſired to ſee an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dept,</hi> yet took no notice of a very great failing; he was too communicative, and his houſe was ſo diſpoſed, that nothing that was done in it could be Secret. He ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſpent Two Hundred Pounds a Year in making Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, and kept ſeveral men to that purpoſe; But his men knew as well as himſelf all that was done, and they were perpetually about him. <hi>Philalehes</hi> preſenrly perceived this dangerous diſpoſition: But in that Viſit, obſerved a Perſon, that happened to be there at the ſame time, who expreſſed ſo much caution in every word he ſpake, that <hi>Philalethes</hi> reſolved to be acquainted with him. He therefore ſaw him, and confirmed the good opinion he had conceived of him, and at once gave him as much of the <hi>White Elixir,</hi> as ſufficed to make 60000 l. <hi>Sterling</hi> worth of <hi>Silver.</hi> What afterwards happened would be to long to recite, and has no more affinity to the preſent Subject. But it doth not appear <hi>Philalethes</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver imparted the Art to him; and he affirms to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58497:24"/>
would not, and he would never preſs him too far for fear of diſpleaſing him. Perhaps he hopes he will do it ſomtime, when he'll think it convenient. And perhaps <hi>Philalethes</hi> has reaſons, beſt known to himſelf, why he ſhould not do it.</p>
                  <p>But in all probability, it is any Great Man's fault, that has a genius this way and that is Virtuous, if he doth not invite <hi>Adepts</hi> to him. For, why can't he be Secret? He is in a capacity to do infinite good, even to his Prince and Country (which is the laſt and alſo the higheſt qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that can be deſired) He need fear nothing. He can be in no danger. His houſe is a Palace. His Retinue are his Guards. He has Favour. He has Acceſs. And 'tis to be preſumed, he is loved and honoured. Beſides, having a vaſt Eſtate, he may Publickly do a vaſt deal of good, and no Body ſtrange at it. And he may do a great deal under hand, and by means of others that depend of him; and ſtill he may keep his Secret to himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Then why can't he fix an inconſiderable part of the Superfluities of his Eſtate to make experiments, as Mr. <hi>B,</hi> did? But he muſt not commit the faults, that that worthy man did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>erve to avoyd. Firſt, he may have his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boratory in a Private place. It need take, in all, no more room than an ordinary Chamber. Let it be divided into two equal parts by a Brick Wall. Then it will make as it were two large, or rather long Cloſets, adjoyning next one another, and only parted by a wall. Let there be two Doors for theſe two Cloſets, a particular Door to each particular Cloſet. Then, into one of theſe two Cloſets no Body need ever to enter but the Maſter himſelf, or at moſt another man more; and that a choice one, as we ſhall particularize by and by. Let there be two ſmall Chimney-Funnells to theſe two Cloſets, a Funnel over each Cloſet; and let each Funnel be, not next to any Wall, but over the middle of the Seeling of each Cloſet, that the Smoak and ill Odours of the Furnaces may be carried out that way, Let the Cloſets Windows be placed as
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58497:24"/>
high as may conveniently be. Now, let two Furnaces, that I ſhall deſcribe, be built ſo, that part of each Furnace may be in one of the Cloſets, and another part in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cloſet. The deſign whereof is, that a Servant may continually ſupply your Fires, ſtanding in one of the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets (which for diſtinction ſake we will call the Servants Cloſet) and never come among your Veſſels that ſhall be placed on the other parts of the Furnaces in the next Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet (which we will call the Maſters Cloſet) where the heat ſhall come. Wherefore the two parts of each Furnace muſt be built immediately joyning the Brick Wall, which divides the Laboratory into two Cloſets, and two ſmall holes muſt be made in the ſaid Wall, to let in the heat from one part of the Furnaces to the other; a hole to that purpoſe for each Furnace. The Furnaces muſt be, the one a Common Wind Furnace, and the other an Athanor. Almoſt all the Wind Furnace will be in that Cloſet which we call the Maſters Cloſet: There will be only the aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole of it, and the hole to put in the Coals, in the Cloſet where the Servant comes But all the Tower of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanor will be in the Servants Cloſet: and the other part of it upon which the Veſſels ſhall ſtand in digeſtion, and all the reſt of the Wind Furnace except the doors, ſhall be in the Maſters Cloſet.</p>
                  <p>The Laboratory, and Furnaces, and all the Utenſils requiſite to make it convenient and fit for the Rich, will not coſt above <hi>50l.</hi> If thou conceiveſt in General the Method of the Art, and wilt work thy ſelf, there needs but one man to do the dirtieſt part of the work, that is, to attend the Fires and put in the Coals, and make the Lutes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If thou wilt not thy ſelf undertake the work, thou muſt have another Man to do it. if thou canſt have one rightly qualified. Two Hundred Pounds a Year, is certainly more than needs to keep theſe two Men, and pay them wages, and furniſh to all the charges of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments But Rich Men may have all their convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; The Labourer is worthy of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And Nobles
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58497:25"/>
muſt do all things Nobly. And what is Two Hundred a Year to ſome great men? It is but an inconſiderable part of what they may ſpare out of the Superfluity of their abundance. Yet, that which is ſo little to them, may all the Year round<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> afford them a Philoſophick trial of the Sublimeſt Speculation; and may be an agreeable Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them at their ſpare hours, when they may ſee what is done in their Laboratory. Beſides, it will be a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for two of their fellow-Creatures; and may be of infinite advantage to themſelves and all the World.</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe you reckon thirty Pounds a piece for the Board of the Men, thats 60 <hi>l.</hi> And 50 <hi>l.</hi> for the wages of the one, and 10 <hi>l.</hi> for the Wages of the other, that's 60 <hi>l.</hi> more. Then there remains 80 <hi>l.</hi> to buy the Coals, year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Veſſells, the Drugs; and thats ſuperaboundant. 'Tis evident, all is here ſet to the utmoſt, however this can break, or be very burthenſome to no great man. To think of greater charges is both needleſs and unreaſonable tho<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I know, ſome have ſpent more; but that was their fault<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For they were deceived by Quacks and Impoſtors, and they little underſtood the ways of Nature, and no more regarded that, than the means to obtain God's Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; eſteeming that expences was the ſure and only means to their end; but they were fruſtrated.</p>
                  <p>If you take two men, one for each Cloſet; the Head Man muſt be thus qualified. 1. He muſt be an Artiſt, 2. He muſt neceſſarily be a Temperate and Virtuous, a Holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sober and Moderate Man; 3. He muſt be a Lover of the Art, and muſt be converſant in the Herme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Writings; 4. He muſt indiſpenſibly be diſcreet and one that is capable of Secreſy; And, 5. One that has no other deſign and thinks of no other Employment, but will oblige himſelf to ſtick to this as long as he lives; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt alſo aſſure him his Penſion for his Life. for in often ſhifting of men, there can be no improvement nor Secreſy. Laſtly, you muſt take an Oath of him that he will be Secret, and, as much as is poſſible, will let no
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58497:25"/>
body (beſides one, which ſhall be you or your heir) know what he works upon, nor the Method he follows, no, not his own Wife if he have one. And you muſt likewiſe make the ſame Oath your ſelf, and vow that if any <hi>Adept</hi> happen to come to communicate himſelf to you, you will Sacredly keep the abovementioned Conditions, as far as in you lieth. There's no Great Man that does this, but may come in time to be as well known to <hi>Adepts</hi> as Mr. <hi>B.</hi> And when it is perceived that he has uſed all theſe cautions, they will be heartily inclined to communicate with him.</p>
                  <p>Now, conſider ſincerely whether that ſmall portion of the Superfluity of your Revenues can be better ſpent. You'll ſay, you are not infallibly aſſured of the <hi>Stone.</hi> No, but there's ground enough to hope; and what you venture cannot hurt ye; and ('tis certain) according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Proverb, <hi>Nothing Venture, Nothing Have.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You'll urge, you might do a great deal of good with that Summ. Yeas, and you may ſtill do a great deal of good beſides, notwithſtanding you conſecrate this to Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iniſtry; for you are but a Steward of your Eſtate: And in this do you not do ſome certain good? Do you not maintain two men, and it may be two Families, eſpecially if you let the Men board themſelves, and you allow them what has been accounted for their board? And do you reckon for nothing the good you may do your ſelf and all men, if you ſucceed?</p>
                  <p>Still, you'll urge; If this Summ was ſpared for your Children, it would amount to ſomthing in time. But have you not enough to ſpare for your Children beſides? And will it not do them good, if it draws God's Bleſſing upon them? And, in time, you or your heirs may get the <hi>Elixir,</hi> which will preſerve you in health and eaſe to the laſt moment of your Life. Beſides, it will yet be conſtantly greater Engagement to you and your Children to be more and more Pious and Virtuous.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:58497:26"/>After all, thoſe that are able and yet think much to lay ſuch a ſumm to this uſe, often do nor think it much to loſe as much or more at Cards, or ſpend it in Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. What? Doſt thou not conſider the wretched condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the generality of Mankind is in, and how miſerably they fare in this evil World, where men wickedly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and devoure one another? And wilt thou do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to attempt to relieve good part of them from the heavy Burthen they groan under? Hard-hearted Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture! The very undertaking would be kind, and would acquit thee. But thou wilt do nothing for the good of Mankind, and it is enough for thee that thou and thine are well. Is that thy Conſcience? is that thy Charity? is that thy Religion? Doth not the well-fare of others at all concern thee? Rare Chriſtian, that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt neither for the Members of Chriſt nor Chriſtianity! For all thy care is to fare well thy ſelf, and flouriſh in the World, and leave thy Family Triumphant, whilſt others creep in the Duſt. Thus are the Heathens and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners diſpoſed; And, therefore, wherein art thou better than they? When thou comeſt into the other World, and it ſhall be ſhewn thee how much good thou mighteſt have done; how many people thou mighteſt have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved; how many uſeful Books thou mighteſt have cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have been Publiſhed; what great things thou mighteſt have undertaken, and what Foundation thou mighteſt have laid for the proſperity of ſucceeding Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations; and it ſhall be examin'd what thou didſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of all this, and whereunto thou haſt employed all thy Talents; what wilt thou be able to ſay? Thy Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Houſes, thy Sports, thy Ambition; will theſe be mentioned with Applauſe? <hi>Thoſe things which are in high eſteem among Men, are Abominations in the ſight of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thy lifting up thy ſelf ſo high above thy fellow Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as if thou wouldeſt be held a Divinity, and would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be Worſhipped of them; Thy Partiality, thy Pride, and Unmercifullneſs in making ſuch a difference betwixt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58497:26"/>
thee and them; Thy Haughtineſs in trampling upon them, and thy Cruelty in contemning and humbling, in afflicting and oppreſſing them, will make thee then be deſpiſed and abhorred. But they ſhall be comforted.</p>
                  <p>The reſult of which Conſideration certainly is this, that thoſe that are Rich in this World, be not High-min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, nor Coveteous; but that they do good; be ready to Diſtribute, and willing to Communicate, that they may lay hold on Eternal Life. Otherwiſe they effectually renounce Chriſtianity; For Charity is the Badge of that Holy Profeſſion: And Chriſtian Charity imports, that we love other men as our ſelves: That indeed did, in the Apoſtolick Age, thoſe truely zealous and ſincere Chriſtians, who were together, and had all things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and parted unto all men as every man had need, and did eat their Meat with gladneſs and ſingleneſs of Heart, in honour preferring one another, Praiſing God, and having favour with all People.</p>
                  <p>That's the thing Eſſential, that we have this Pious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that we love other men as our ſelves. There may be ſome doubts in <hi>Philoſophy;</hi> but there can be non in this, that this is certainly our Duty. And therefore thoſe that are Rich, ought not to think it much, to haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard ſomething of what thy can ſpare, to aim at an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal good.</p>
                  <p>I do not pretend to a Demonſtration of the <hi>Elixir:</hi> But I do think there are credible grounds, to believe that there is ſuch a thing and that it may be had. And if ſo, then ſurely it is reaſonable to venture ſomething for it.</p>
                  <p>When I give my ſelf the Title of <hi>Philadept,</hi> the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of that is not that I am actually acquainted with any <hi>Adept,</hi> but that I am a well-wiſher to them. I my ſelf never ſaw one, that I know; But I doubt not there are ſome men Living have reaſon to think they have<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For, Sincerely, there are great reaſons to conclude of ſome men that they were <hi>Adepts.</hi> If ſo, it were to be wiſhed they had left the Principles of the Art, both with
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58497:27"/>
men that ſhould direct the ſame to the beſt end, (the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral good of mankind,) and with Skillful Artiſts, who were both able and willing to make a good uſe of it. But, whatever Judgment may be made of the Philoſophy of <hi>Hermes,</hi> I conclude with this infallible deciſion of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly Wiſe Man: <hi>The Fear of the Lord, that's Wiſdom; And to depart from Evil, that is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58497:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
